1909 Hudson-Fulton Celebration Collection
Marist College Archives and Special Collections
- 8. Badges, Medals, and Pins, 1909; 12.0 linear feet 12 Box (Box 10 -, Box 22)
  - Subseries 8.1: Badges and Medals, 1909; 10.0 linear feet 10 Box (Box 10 -, Box 20)
    - HF Holland Society of New York Badge, Backing ribbon discolored and fraying along bottom edge. Silver plating on top bar and backing of “Half-Moon” medal. Small stain on upper center of reverse of ribbon. Various scratches across obverse and reverse of medal. Fingerprint visible on obverse bottom of metal where plating has worn away. (Box 18)
      Silver plated pin attached to orange ribbon featuring medal with “Half-Moon” design. Top bar reads “1609/ 1909/ Holland Society/ Of New York/ Henry Hudson/ 300th Anniversary.” “Half-Moon” medal features brass image of ship over half-moon-shaped backing. Maker’s mark on reverse of medal for Robbins Co., Attleboro, MA.
    - HF Celebration Ringgold Hose Co. Member Badge, Tarnish across both faces and top bar. Tarnish more prominent on reverse. Patina present around center image on medal obverse. Gilded lettering is discolored and missing most of the gold. (Box 18)
      Brass member medal for Ringgold Hose Co No. 1, featuring red ribbon. Top bar reads “Member”. Ribbon reads “Ringgold/ Hose Co. No. 1/ Hudson-Fulton/ Celebration/ Newburgh, N.Y./ Sept. 30, 1909.” Medal features image of Ringgold fire engine and fire fighters aboard truck. Maker’s mark on reverse for Whitehead & Hoag.
    - HF Celebration Ringgold Hose Co. Guest Badge, Tarnish across both faces and top bar. Tarnish more prominent on reverse. Gilded lettering is discolored and missing some gold. (Box 18)
      Brass guest medal for Ringgold Hose Co No. 1, featuring red ribbon. Top bar reads “Guest”. Ribbon reads “Ringgold/ Hose Co. No. 1/ Hudson-Fulton/ Celebration/ Newburgh, N.Y./ Sept. 30, 1909.” Medal features image of Ringgold fire engine and fire fighters aboard truck. Maker’s mark on reverse for Whitehead & Hoag.
    - HF Cross Pattée-Shaped Souvenir Medal With Tri-Colored Ribbon, Tarnish across both faces of medal and top bar. Small spot of rust on obverse bottom edge of center coin. Small dark spot of tarnish on top bar obverse right center. Small areas of discoloration on ribbon and beginnings of fray along edges. (Box 18)
      Souvenir medal for the Hudson-Fulton Celebration featuring a cross pattée-shaped outer frame with a brass coin in its center. Top bar reads “souvenir”. Tri-colored ribbon (red, white, and blue), reads “Hudson/ Fulton/ Celebration/ New York/ Sept. 25 to Oct. 9th/ 1909. Center coin features image of “Clermont” on obverse and “the Lord’s Prayer” on reverse. Outer frame intricately designed.
    - HF Cross Pattée-Shaped Lord’s Prayer Medal With Tri-Colored Ribbon, Ribbon is discolored. Patina present along outer edges of coin in center of medal. (Box 18)
      Cross pattée-shaped medal featuring brass in coin in center in commemoration of the Hudson-Fulton Celebration. Obverse of coin features portraits of both Hudson and Fulton below banner for the celebration. Reverse of coin features “The Lord’s Prayer” in its entirety. Outer frame of medal is intricately designed copper. Top ribbon is tri-colored with colors of Dutch flag.
    - HF Cross Pattée-Shaped Lord’s Prayer Medal, Dark tarnish across both faces. Suspension ring is broken. Small stain or spot of residue on obverse right and reverse left. (Box 18)
      Cross pattée-shaped medal featuring brass in coin in center in commemoration of the Hudson-Fulton Celebration. Obverse of coin features portraits of both Hudson and Fulton below banner for the celebration. Reverse of coin features “The Lord’s Prayer” in its entirety. Outer frame of medal is intricately designed and has a suspension ring at the top center.
    - HF Cross Patonce-Shaped Copper Souvenir Ships Medal, Ribbon has large stain on obverse center. Faint tarnish across both faces. Patina present along outer edge of center coin and on reverse of top bar below brooch. (Box 18)
      Cross patonce-shaped copper medal featuring brass coin in center. Obverse of coin features images of both “Half-Moon” and “Clermont”. Reverse of coin features “The Lord’s Prayer” in its entirety. Outer, copper frame is intricately designed and reads “Hudson-Fulton Celebration/ New York/ Sept. 25/ Oct. 2/ 1909.” Top bar is shaped like “Clermont” and reads “Souvenir.” Ribbon is orange and white. Maker’s mark on reverse for Schwaab S.S. & Co.
    - HF West Grove, NJ Fire Department Member Medal, Dark tarnish across both faces. Staining or residue across reverse. Small spot of possible corrosion on top bar obverse center. (Box 18)
      Circular medal featuring New York State Coat of Arms in center on obverse below image of fireman’s helmet and tool. Obverse reads “Hudson-Fulton Celebration/ Newburgh, NY Sept. 30, 1909/ Unexcelled/ No. 2/ West Grove, NJ. Obverse of top bar features images of ladder and torch. Top bar reads “Member”. Medal is suspended by chain from top bar. Maker’s mark on reverse for Whitehead & Hoag Co.
    - HF Tercentenary Celebration Brass-Plated Souvenir Medal, Tarnish across both faces of top bar. Brass-plating on medal Has worn along outer edges and across raised portions of design on both faces. Ribbon is separated from top bar and is fraying along top and bottom edges. Ribbon is discolored and has small stains across obverse bottom. Small tears in reverse bottom right of ribbon. (Box 18)
      Brass-plated circular medal featuring portraits of both Hudson and Fulton on obverse below banner for Hudson-Fulton Celebration. Reverse reads “Souvenir/ Hudson-Fulton/ Tercentenary/ Celebration/ 1609/ 1807/ 1909/ New York. Maker’s mark on reverse for T.J. Dunn & Co. Top bar reads “Souvenir”. Ribbon is tri-colored with colors of Dutch flag. Ribbon reads “Hudson/ Fulton/ Celebration/ New York/ Sept. 25th Oct. 9th/ 1909.”
    - HF Celebration Commission Official Guest Medal, Most of the silver-plating on top bar has worn away. Silver-plating has also worn away on reverse, outer edges, and edges of obverse on medal. Ribbon is discolored. Top ribbon is faintly stained across top. Backing, orange ribbon is frayed across bottom edge and features several creases. (Box 18)
      Silver-plated medal featuring Dutch flag as front ribbon with orange backing ribbon. Top bar reads “Guest.” Obverse features portraits of Hudson and Fulton. Edges read “Henry Hudson 1609/ Robert Fulton 1807/ 1909”. Reverse features image of Lady Columbia holding the “Half-Moon” and “Clermont” in each hand with background of NYC skyline. Edges read “Hudson-Fulton/ Celebration”.
    - Hudson-Fulton Citizens’ Comm. Medal #3, Tarnish across center of obverse of top bar. Faint tarnish across both faces of medal. Ribbon is discolored. (Box 18)
    - HF Albany, NY Bronze All Nations Badge, Nearly all silver-plating on medal has worn away. Tarnish across both faces of top bars. Toning across both faces of medal. Backing ribbon discolored and is fraying along bottom edge. Small tear on upper right of ribbon. Lettering on ribbon is visible on obverse. (Box 18)
      Bronze and silver-plated All Nations badge pin for the Hudson-Fulton Celebration in Albany, NY. Silver-plated medal suspended from badge features portrait of Hudson and Fulton on obverse and Albany, NY Coat of Arms on reverse. Obverse reads “Hudson Fulton/ 1609-1909” and reverse reads “City of Albany/ 1909/ Hudson-Fulton Celebration.” Top bars read “Albany, NY/ 1909/ Hudson-Fulton Celebration” and “All Nations”. Backing tri-colored ribbon features colors of Dutch flag. Masker’s mark on reverse of ribbon for Quayle.
    - HF Celebration Silver-Plated Souvenir Medal, Silver plating has worn in several places across both faces of medal and top bar. Nearly all plating around and below brooch on reverse of top bar has worn away. Ribbon is slightly discolored. (Box 18)
      Silver-plated medal featuring portraits of Hudson and Fulton obverse. Reverse features images of “Half-Moon” and “Clermont”. Reverse reads “Hudson-Fulton/ Celebration/ 1909/ New York Sept. 25. Oct. 9.” Top bar reads “Souvenir”. Ribbon is tri-colored with colors of Dutch flag and reads “Hudson/ Fulton/ Celebration/ New York/ Sept. 25 to Oct. 9th/ 1909.
    - HF Celebration Silver-Plated Souvenir Medal #2, Silver plating has worn in several places across both faces of medal. Most of the plating on both faces of top bar has worn away. Ribbon is slightly discolored and features several areas of white around edges. (Box 18)
    - HF Celebration Traffic Club Medal, Most of the silver-plating has worn across both faces of medal and top bar. Ribbon is discolored. Ribbon has torn and frayed and is separating from top bar. (Box 18)
      Silver-plated medal features seal of New York Traffic Club on obverse center. Obverse reads “Traffic Club/ New York.” Top bar reads “1609 /1909/ Hudson-Fulton.” Ribbon is tri-colored with colors of Dutch flag. Maker’s mark on reverse for Whitehead & Hoag Co.
    - HF Celebration Traffic Club Medal #2, Most of the silver-plating has worn across both faces of medal and top bar. Ribbon is discolored. (Box 18)
    - HF Tercentenary Celebration Copper-Plated Souvenir Medal, Nearly all copper-plating has worn away on both faces. Small amounts remain along obverse right edge and reverse left edge and top center. Potential corrosion on the inside of suspension ring. (Box 19)
      Copper-plated circular medal featuring portraits of both Hudson and Fulton on obverse below banner for Hudson-Fulton Celebration. Reverse reads “Souvenir/ Hudson-Fulton/ Tercentenary/ Celebration/ 1609/ 1807/ 1909/ New York. Maker’s mark on reverse for T.J. Dunn & Co. Suspension ring in top center.
    - HF Tercentenary Celebration Copper-Plated Souvenir Medal #2, Most copper-plating has worn away across obverse and nearly all on reverse. Dark spots of tarnish on reverse left and right edge. Potential corrosion on the inside of suspension ring. (Box 19)
    - HF Tercentenary Celebration Copper-Plated Souvenir Medal #3, Most copper-plating has worn away across both faces. Dark spots of tarnish on reverse left and right edge. Potential corrosion on the inside of suspension ring. (Box 19)
    - HF Tercentenary Celebration Silver-Plated Souvenir Medal, Plating has worn away along outer edges and edges of faces. Small area with no plating on reverse lower right. Potential corrosion on the inside of suspension ring. (Box 19)
      Silver-plated circular medal featuring portraits of both Hudson and Fulton on obverse below banner for Hudson-Fulton Celebration. Reverse reads “Souvenir/ Hudson-Fulton/ Tercentenary/ Celebration/ 1609/ 1807/ 1909/ New York. Maker’s mark on reverse for T.J. Dunn & Co. Suspension ring in top center.
    - HF Tercentenary Celebration Brass-Plated Souvenir Medal, Plating has worn away along outer edges and on raised portions of design on both faces. (Box 19)
      Brass-plated circular medal featuring portraits of both Hudson and Fulton on obverse below banner for Hudson-Fulton Celebration. Reverse reads “Souvenir/ Hudson-Fulton/ Tercentenary/ Celebration/ 1609/ 1807/ 1909/ New York. Maker’s mark on reverse for T.J. Dunn & Co. Suspension ring in top center.
    - HF Tercentenary Celebration Brass-Plated Souvenir Medal #2, Plating has worn away along outer edges and on raised portions of design on both faces. Small spot of potential patina or residue on reverse top right edge. (Box 19)
    - HF Tercentenary Celebration Brass-Plated Souvenir Medal #3, Nearly all brass-plating has worn away across both faces. Only small amounts remain in centers of both faces. Dark tarnish across base medal on reverse. (Box 19)
    - Gilded HF Celebration Newburgh, NY Medal, Small, dark spots of tarnish across both faces and outer edges. (Box 19)
      Previously gilded medal featuring portraits of both Hudson and Fulton on obverse. Reverse features image of feminine figure seated above ships on Hudson River. Reverse reads “Oct/ 1st 09/ Newburgh.” Maker’s mark on outer edge for Whitehead & Hoag Co.
    - Gilded HF Celebration Newburgh, NY Medal #2, Gilt has worn away in several small areas across both faces. Several small scratches across both faces where gilt is damaged and base medal is visible. (Box 19)
      Gilded medal featuring portraits of both Hudson and Fulton on obverse. Reverse features image of feminine figure seated above ships on Hudson River. Reverse reads “Oct/ 1st 09/ Newburgh.” Maker’s mark on outer edge for Whitehead & Hoag Co.
    - Gilded HF Celebration Newburgh, NY Medal #3, Most of gilt has worn away or tarnished. Several large scratches, resembling brush strokes, where gilt is missing revealing base medal. (Box 19)
    - Circle of Friends of the Medallion Medal One #3, Tarnish across both faces. Patina present along outer edges. (Box 19)
      Bronze, die-struck Hudson-Fulton Celebration commemorative medal issued by the Circle of Friends of the Medallion. The medal was the first in the series issued in 1909. The medal was designed and cast by John Flanagan (1865-1962). Front of metal features images of Hudson and Fulton. Obverse reads Henry Hudson/ Robert Fulton/ MDCIX”. Reverse of metal features image of female figure lying upon clouds, holding a lightbulb to symbolize the age of electricity. In the background are the “Half-Moon” and “Clermont” on the Hudson River before the New York City skyline. Back reads “MDCIX MDCCCVII/ MDCIX”.
    - HF Celebration Portrait Crest-Shaped Medal, Gilt has worn away in several places across both faces. Base metal is tarnished on both faces. Small, dark spot of unknown residue on obverse top right. (Box 19)
      Gilded, crest-shaped medal featuring portraits of both Hudson and Fulton on obverse. Obverse reads “Hudson-Fulton/ Celebration/ New York/ Sept. 25-Oct. 2/ 1909.” Maker’s mark on reverse for Schwaab S.S. & Co. Suspension rings in top center.
    - HF Scalloped-Edge Half-Moon Medal, Most plating on medal has worn away. Base metal and remaining plating tarnished. (Box 19)
      Scalloped-edge, plated medal featuring metallic image of Hudson’s “Half-Moon”. Edge of obverse reads “Henrick Hudson/ 1609.” Suspension rings in top center.
    - HF Poughkeepsie, NY Celebration Medal, Silver-plating has worn and tarnished across both faces. Small red staining on reverse center right. Small spots of dark tarnish or possible residue on obverse center. (Box 19)
      Silver-plated medal featuring portraits of Hudson, Fulton, and possible Dr. E. Parmly Brown on the obverse. Obverse reads “October Fourth/ 1909”. Reverse features image of Poughkeepsie Bridge with “Clermont” on the Hudson River below. Hole punched in top center.
    - HF Celebration New York to Albany Gilded Medal, Gilding has worn away along edges and raised portions of design on reverse. (Box 19)
      Gilded medal featuring portraits of Hudson and Fulton on front and images of “Half-Moon” and “Clermont” on back. Front lettering reads “Hudson-Fulton/ Celebration/ Sept. 25 to Oct. 9/ 1909”. Back lettering reads “New York to Albany/ Half Moon 1609/ Clermont 1807.” Suspension ring in top center.
    - HF Albany, NY Silver-Plated Coat of Arms Medal, Hole in top center damaged along top. (Box 19)
      Silver-plated medal for the Hudson-Fulton Celebration in Albany, NY. Medal features portrait of Hudson and Fulton on obverse and Albany, NY Coat of Arms on reverse. Obverse reads “Hudson Fulton/ 1609-1909” and reverse reads “City of Albany/ 1909/ Hudson-Fulton Celebration.” Hole punched in top center.
    - HF Albany, NY Silver-Plated Coat of Arms Medal #2, Plating has worn away in several places along outline of design and lettering on both faces. Small, dark spots along obverse right. (Box 19)
    - HF Albany, NY Silver-Plated Coat of Arms Medal #3, Most plating has worn away around edges of both faces. (Box 19)
      Silver-plated medal for the Hudson-Fulton Celebration in Albany, NY. Medal features portrait of Hudson and Fulton on obverse and Albany, NY Coat of Arms on reverse. Obverse reads “Hudson Fulton/ 1609-1909” and reverse reads “City of Albany/ 1909/ Hudson-Fulton Celebration.” Suspension rings in top center.
    - HF Albany, NY Silver-Plated Coat of Arms Medal #4, Most plating has worn away around edges of both faces. (Box 19)
    - New York Coat of Arms HF Souvenir Coin Badge, Faint toning across both faces of coin. Various faint scratches across both faces of coin and top bar. Reverse of top bar has small spot of tarnish on top center. Corrosion present on adhesive below brooch on reverse of top bar. (Box 20)
      Metal badge featuring suspended coin depicting portraits of Hudson and Fulton. Obverse of coin reads “Hudson-Fulton Celebration/ New York 1909.” Top bar is in the shape of “Clermont” and reads “Souvenir.” Reverse features image of New York State Coat of Arms. Maker’s mark on reverse for Schwaab S. & S. Co. Adhesive under brooch visible on reverse of top bar.
    - New York Coat of Arms HF Souvenir Coin Badge #2, Small spots of potential rust across top of obverse of coin. Small, dark spots of tarnish around outer edges of coin and across reverse of top bar. Possible corrosion present on adhesive below brooch on back of top bar. (Box 20)
      Medal featuring suspended coin depicting portraits of Hudson and Fulton. Obverse of coin reads “Hudson-Fulton Celebration/ New York 1909.” Top bar is in the shape of “Clermont” and reads “Souvenir.” Reverse features image of New York State Coat of Arms. Maker’s mark on reverse for Schwaab S. & S. Co. Adhesive under brooch visible on reverse of top bar.
    - New York Coat of Arms HF Souvenir Coin Badge #3, Small spots of potential rust across top of obverse of coin. Small, dark spots of tarnish around outer edges of coin and across reverse of top bar. Possible corrosion present on adhesive below brooch on back of top bar. (Box 20)
    - Circular Portrait HF Souvenir Badge, Various, small scratches across both faces. Large spot of rust on reverse center of pin. Tarnish across both faces of pin and top bar. Faint toning visible on both faces of pin. (Box 20)
      Medal, circular badge featuring portraits of Hudson and Fulton below banner for Hudson-Fulton Celebration. Top bar reads “Souvenir”. Adhesive under brooch visible on reverse of top bar.
    - Circular Portrait HF Souvenir Badge #2, Various faint scratches across both faces of pin and top bar. Small spots of rust on reverse of pin in center and along bottom center edge. Small indentation on reverse left of pin. (Box 20)
      Metal, circular badge featuring portraits of Hudson and Fulton below banner for Hudson-Fulton Celebration. Top bar reads “Souvenir”. Adhesive under brooch visible on reverse of top bar.
    - HF Celebration Flags and Portrait Badge #1-2, Various small scratches across reverse of pin. Faint toning visible across reverse of pine—more prominent on one pin. (Box 20)
      Metal badge featuring portraits of Hudson and Fulton below color flags of the United States and Holland. Obverse reads “Hudson-Fulton Celebration/ Hudson/ Fulton/ Sept. 25, 1909.” Top bar reads “1609/ New York/ 1909.” Maker’s mark on reverse for Chas M. Robbing Co. Adhesive below brooch visible on reverse of top bar.
    - HF Celebration Clermont with Ships and Portraits Badge, Slight tarnish across both faces of pin and top bar. Small spots of rust across obverse of pin. Large spot of rust across bottom of reverse of pin. Corrosion present on adhesive below brooch on reverse of top bar. (Box 20)
      Metal badge featuring portraits of Hudson and Fulton beside images of “Half-Moon” and “Clermont”. Top bar is in the shape of “Clermont” and reads “Souvenir.” Obverse reads “Hudson-Fulton/ Celebration/ 1609/ 1807/ New York/ Sept. 25- Oct. 2/ 1909.” Maker’s mark for Schwaab S. & S. Co.
    - HF Celebration Clermont with Ships and Portraits Badge #2, Slight tarnish across both faces of pin and top bar. Tarnish more pronounced along edges on reverse. Patina present on adhesive below where brooch is missing on reverse of top bar. (Box 20)
      Metal badge featuring portraits of Hudson and Fulton beside images of “Half-Moon” and “Clermont”. Top bar is in the shape of “Clermont” and reads “Souvenir.” Obverse reads “Hudson-Fulton/ Celebration/ 1609/ 1807/ New York/ Sept. 25- Oct. 2/ 1909.” Maker’s mark on reverse for Schwaab S. & S. Co. Adhesive under brooch visible on reverse of top bar.
    - HF Celebration Half-Moon and Clermont Souvenir Badge, Various small scratches across both faces. Small, darker spot of tarnish on reverse left of pin. Small indentation in upper right of reverse of pin. Small spots of tarnish beside images of ships on obverse. (Box 20)
      Metal badge featuring images of “Half-Moon” and “Clermont” on obverse. Bottom of obverse reads “Hudson-Fulton Celebration. New York. 1909.” Top bar reads “Souvenir”. Adhesive visible below brooch on reverse of top bar.
    - HF Celebration Half-Moon and Clermont Souvenir Badge #2, Small spot of rust along left edge of reverse of pin. Various scratches across both faces of pin and top bar. Unknown residue on reverse of pin in rectangular shape—possibly from sticker. Small indentation in upper right of reverse of pin. More pronounced scratches along edges of both faces of top bar. (Box 20)
    - HF Celebration Half-Moon and Clermont Souvenir Badge #3, Much of the outer plating has been worn away on reverse of pin and top bar. Some plating has worn along left edge of obverse of top bar and pin. Patina present along suspension rings and holes. Patina present beneath brooch on reverse of top bar. More significant scratches and dark tarnishing on reverse of top bar. Small spots of darker tarnish on right edge of reverse of pin. (Box 20)
    - HF Celebration Half-Moon and Clermont Souvenir Badge #4, Various small scratches across both faces. Small, darker spot of tarnish on reverse bottom center of pin. Small indentation in upper right of reverse of pin. Various, very small spots of dark tarnish across top of reverse of pin. (Box 20)
    - HF Dutch Flag Top Bar Half-Moon Badge, Various small scratches across both faces of pin. Faint toning visible on reverse of pin. Faint tarnish along edges of top bar. Corrosion visible on adhesive below brooch on reverse of top bar. Small spot of tarnish on obverse top center of pin. (Box 20)
      Metal badge featuring image of Hudson’s landing of the “Half-Moon” on the Hudson River below banner for Hudson-Fulton Celebration. Bottom of obverse reads “Hudson/ Landing From Half Moon/ New York/ 1909.” Top bar reads “Souvenir” and features background of Dutch flag colors. Maker’s mark for Schwaab S. & S. Co.
    - HF Celebration Souvenir Landing of Half-Moon Badge, Metal pin featuring image of Hudson’s landing of the “Half-Moon” on the Hudson River below banner for Hudson-Fulton Celebration. Top bar reads “Souvenir”. Adhesive visible on reverse of top bar. Maker’s mark for Schwaab S. & S. Co. (Box 20)
      Metal badge featuring image of Hudson’s landing of the “Half-Moon” on the Hudson River below banner for Hudson-Fulton Celebration. Top bar reads “Souvenir”. Adhesive visible on reverse of top bar. Maker’s mark for Schwaab S. & S. Co.
    - HF Celebration Eagle and Half-Moon Landing Souvenir Badge, Metal pin featuring image of Hudson’s landing of the “Half-Moon” on the Hudson River below banner for Hudson-Fulton Celebration. Top of obverse reads “New York” below image of eagle. Top bar reads “Souvenir”. Pin suspended from top bar by two chains. Adhesive visible on reverse of top bar. (Box 20)
    - HF Celebration Eagle and Half-Moon Landing Souvenir Badge #2, Metal pin featuring image of Hudson’s landing of the “Half-Moon” on the Hudson River below banner for Hudson-Fulton Celebration. Top of obverse reads “New York” below image of eagle. Top bar reads “Souvenir”. Pin suspended from top bar by two chains. Adhesive visible on reverse of top bar. (Box 20)